Guide to the Max Black papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
Black, Max papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Max Black papers, [ca. 1927]-1988.
14-21-2466
Max Black, 1909-
32.0 cubic ft.
Correspondence, files, and a manuscript.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Professional papers include correspondence, subject files, and files relating to his work with the Science, Technology, and Society program at Cornell. Also, manuscript of Black's book Rational Choice, the Prisoner's Dilemma.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Philosopher, Professor of Philosophy at Cornell University.
Max Black received two doctoral degrees from the University of London. He taught at the University of London from 1936 to 1940 and at the University of Illinois from 1940 to 1946. He joined the faculty at Cornell in 1946, becoming the Susan Linn Sage Professor of Philosophy in 1954. In 1965, Black became the first director of Cornell's Society for the Humanities, a position he held until 1971. Since 1971, he was a member of the Cornell program on Science, Technology and Society and academic head of its Unit on Humanities, Science and Technology. His first publication was a discussion of Jeremy Bentham's theory of definition. He has written numerous works on philosophical subjects, including books on mathematics, Wittgenstein, and the nature of the university.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Professional papers include correspondence, subject files, and files relating to his work with the Science, Technology, and Society program at Cornell. Also, manuscript of Black's book Rational Choice, the Prisoner's Dilemma.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Black, Max, 1909-1988; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Philosophy--Study and teaching.; Philosophers.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 31 and 32 are restricted until the death of the donors or by their permission.
CONTAINER LIST
- Probability; Induction; Mss. (Past); Cornell University matters; Fellowships & Grants; Lectures; Publications, Society for Humanities, 1940s-[1960s] (Box 1)
- Papers; Testimonials; reprints of his writings, 1940s-[ ] (Box 2)
- Course files; Paper on Necessity; Alphabetical file A-Z; Notes A-P on various philosophical subjects (Box 3)
- Notes P-W on various philosophical subjects; Tractatus by Wittgenstein (notes and papers) (Box 4)
- Wittgenstein continued; Writing Projects (notes, course notes, arranged alphabetically A-S); Social Science (course notes, reprints, etc.) (Box 5)
- Course work, notes, drafts, papers, reprints on philosophical topics, 1928-[1950s-1960s] (Box 6)
- Course work for systematics; Philosophy of Science course material; India (1962); Japan (1957); Philosophy of Education, [1960s] (Box 7)
- Reprints by others; Topics (notes and papers); Seminars (Past); Tarners Lecture, [1960s]-1978 (Box 8)
- Logic, [1950s-1960s] (Box 9)
- Course material; Academic; reprints, [1960s] (Box 10)
- Bound typescript copies of papers by others; Logical Possibility by M.B. (bd. typsc.) - 2 cassettes (Box 11)
- Alphabetical Subject Files; Misc. I & J, Knowledge, Language, Literary Criticism, Logic, Measurement, Metaphors, Moore and "O", [1970s-1980s] (Box 12)
- Subject Files continued, O-R: Observation, Paradoxes, Philosophy, Practical Reasoning, Probability, Rationality, Reasonable Rules, Russell, [1970s] (Box 13)
- Subject Files continued, S-W: Scholarly Responsibility, Sets, Should and Is, Technion Papers, Technology, University (Open), Verifiability, [1970s] (Box 14)
- Wittgenstein continued; Misc. in separate drawer, incl. Lord Ashby, Humbug, [1970s] (Box 15)
- Professional alpha file A-W incls i.e. C.U. Adult Univ.; Financial, [1970s-1980s] (Box 16)
- Professional alphabetical files I-W; Trips (old), [1970s-1980s] (Box 17)
- Subject files; reprints of M. Black; India, [1970s-1980s] (Box 18)
- Typescripts Memoir of M.B. (Rosenbaum, interviewer); cassettes of lectures; notes (Box 19)
- Notes on philosophical subjects: incl. Tarners Lecture series, [1960s-1970s] (Box 20)
- Philosophical files incl. Tarners Lecture, [1970s-1980s] (Box 21)
- Alpha file: M-Skepticism, Science, Spare, "P"; course material, [1970s] (Box 22)
- Course material; Other Papers; Dromoland Papers, 1972, [1970s] (Box 23)
- Course material; notes and papers, [1960s] (Box 24)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence A-D, [1970s]-1980s (Box 25)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence E-L, [1970s] (Box 26)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence L-R, [1970s] (Box 27)
- Alphabetical files: Correspondence S-Z, [1970s] (Box 28)
- Subject files, A-I: Aspen Colloquium, Communication; Determinism; Explanation; Goodman; Humanism; Humanities, Induction, [1970s] (Box 29)
- Humanities Science and Technology - Rockefeller Foundation, Correspondence and Proposals, Annual Reports, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Humanities Science and Technology - Annual Reports, Colloquia, Workshops, [1970s] (Box 30)
- NEH and NSF - Proposals, Grants and Correspondence, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Publications, [1970s] (Box 30)
- Max Black's Memoir, including original tape recordings from oral interview, 1987 (Box 30)
- Letters to Rosenbaum and Naomi Black, 1961-1987 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  Access restrictions apply
- Letters to Michal, 1931-1941, 1972, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
  With a few replies
- Letters to Michal, 1932-1941, 1957, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
- Letters to Michal, 1932-1936, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
- Letters to Michal, 1932-1945, 1961-1963 (Box 31, Folder 5)
- Letters from Michal, 1931-1933, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Letters from Michal (and Flossie), 1932 (Box 31, Folder 7)
- Daily Agendas, 1932, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
- Daily Agendas, 1955, 1967-1987, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
  Includes expense logs; notes; doodles
- A Companion to Wittgenstein's 'Tractatus' by Max Black, 1964 (Box 31)
- Diary, 1954-1955 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  Written in examination books
- Diary, 1956 (Box 32, Folder 2)
- Diary, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 3)
- Diary, 1959 (Box 32, Folder 4)
- Diary, 1960 (Box 32, Folder 5)
- Diary, 1961 (Box 32, Folder 6)
- Diary, 1962 (Box 32, Folder 7)
- Diary, 1963 (Box 32, Folder 8)
- Diary, 1964 (Box 32, Folder 9)
- Diary, 1965 (Box 32, Folder 10)
- Diary, 1966 (Box 32, Folder 11)
- Diary, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 12)
- Diary, 1968 (Box 32, Folder 13)
- Diary, 1969 (Box 32, Folder 14)
- Diary, 1970 (Box 32, Folder 15)
- Diary, 1971 (Box 32, Folder 16)
- Diary, 1972 (Box 32, Folder 17)
- Diary, 1973 (Box 32, Folder 18)
- Diary, 1974 (Box 32, Folder 19)
- Diary, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 20)
- Diary, 1976 (Box 32, Folder 21)
- Diary, 1977 (Box 32, Folder 22)
- Diary, 1978 (Box 32, Folder 23)
- Diary, 1979 (Box 32, Folder 24)
- Diary, 1980 (Box 32, Folder 25)
- Diary, 1981 (Box 32, Folder 26)
- Diary, 1982 (Box 32, Folder 27)
- Diary, 1983 (Box 32, Folder 28)
- Diary, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 29)
- Diary, 1985-1986 (Box 32, Folder 30)
- General (Travel, Events of Note, etc.), 1950-1982 (Box 32, Folder 31)
- Estate, Memorial Service, 1988-1990 (Box 32, Folder 32)
  Correspondence
- Mabel Michal Black, 1958, 1983-1987, undated (Box 32, Folder 33)
  Includes medicine bills, vaccination record, passports, correspondence, death certificates
- Assorted Correspondence, 1977-1988, undated (Box 32, Folder 34)
  Includes bills, receipts, permission letters, publishing letters
- Letters, 1931-1938, undated (Box 32, Folder 35)
- Letters - M. Macdonald, 1932-1937 (Box 32, Folder 36)
- Personalia (Personal + Miscellaneous), ca. 1911, 1953, 1974, 1985-1986, undated (Box 32, Folder 37)
  Contains letter, infant lock of hair, copy of text, Mind Association members' addresses; letter from Mrs. Ashton Edwards; "philosopher + fish" quote
- Naturalization Records, 1931-1949, undated (Box 32, Folder 38)
  Includes "alien registration receipt card," registration receipts, immigrant identification cards, identity cards, correspondence
- Birth Certificates, etc., 1911, 1933-1949 (Box 32, Folder 39)
  Includes marriage registration, birth certificates, certificate of naturalization
- Sir Misha Black, 1974-1977 (Box 32, Folder 40)
  Correspondence; newspaper clipping of obituary
- Documents - Miscellaneous, 1931, 1948 (Box 32, Folder 41)
  Includes certificate of naturalization, an oath of allegiance
- Rivka - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 32, Folder 42)
- Max Black: Testimonials - Selected Copies, 1931-1939 (Box 32, Folder 43)
- Willie (and Sylina) - Their Daughter, Elisabeth Halpern - Correspondence, 1939-1940, 1977, 1993 (Box 32, Folder 44)
- "Perplexities" - Duplicates, 1952, 1974, 1984-1986 (Box 32, Folder 45)
  Research papers
- Cornell Press - Business '88, 1970, 1987, undated (Box 32, Folder 46)
  Contains argument for 'Perplexities,' text of "The 'Factual' and the 'Normative',"
- England, 1955 (Box 32, Folder 47)
  Includes correspondence, bank notes, material related to King Alfred School
- Japan: Photos, Letters, Visiting Cards, 1957 (Box 32, Folder 48)
  Includes small notebook of Japanese phrases, daily logs, expense logs, dresses, passport info; envelope of newspaper clippings
- Testimonials, 1965 (Box 32, Folder 49)
  Includes correspondence and letters of recommendation
- Letters (Miscellaneous), 1966-1968, undated (Box 32, Folder 50)
  Includes photo of Christopher + Felicity Gittenden (?) when they were children
- KEEP (Assorted Documents), 1942-1955, undated (Box 32, Folder 51)
  Correspondence; book lists; handwritten notes; flyer for "Special University Lectures in Philosophy" at the University of London
- Gregory Vlastos, 1986-03 (Box 32, Folder 52)
- Eric Ashby, 1985-12-08 (Box 32, Folder 53)
  One letter
- Alice Lazerowitz, 1987-07-29 (Box 32, Folder 54)
- Raymond Klibansky, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 55)
- Mark G. Singer, 1969, 1977, 1983, 1987 (Box 32, Folder 56)
  Correspondence; copy of Life with Father, Life with Socrates by Virginia Wetherbee; copy of Are There Any Philosophically Interesting Questions in Technology?; includes two letters from Vicky, one is written on a Harvard College Library transaction card
- M.B. Letters, 1966-1978 (Box 32, Folder 57)
- Rosenbaum, P. + N., 1975-1980, undated (Box 32, Folder 58)
  Correspondence; packet titled "Hints for Life in Jerusalem"
- Posthumous Publication of Perplexities, 1988-1989, undated (Box 32, Folder 59)
  Correspondence; draft of foreword of text
- Possible Posthumous Collection; Other "Lecturing and executive" staff, 1988-1993, undated (Box 32, Folder 60)
- Estate: Mainly Permissions, etc., 1985-1996, undated (Box 32, Folder 61)
- School Reports, 1923-1926 (Box 32, Folder 62)
- Assorted Material, 1924-1938, 1946-1956, 1982-1988, undated (Box 32, Folder 63)
  Includes postcards, rent account summaries, loan and savings books; original envelope labeled "Odds and ends"
- Photographs - Max and Michal Black, Undated (Box 32, Folder 64)
- Photographs - Family and Travel, 1948-1964, 1974-1986, undated (Box 32, Folder 65)
  Includes undated note
- Photographs - School and Family, 1941, 1966-1973, undated (Box 32, Folder 66)
  Includes correspondence from the National Endowment for the Humanities; photo negatives
- Photographs - Seminars/Lectures and Leisure Time, 1966, 1974, undated (Box 32, Folder 67)
- Photographs - Assorted, 1952-1966, undated (Box 32, Folder 68)
  A photo of Ludwig Wittgenstein
- Photographs - Assorted, 1970-1983, undated (Box 32, Folder 69)
  Photo negatives
- Miscellaneous, 1952, 1961, undated (Box 32, Folder 70)
  Includes pages from Picture Post on various philosophy professors, newspaper clipping of philosopher Bertrand Russell, pictures of Ludwig Wittgenstein, Albert Einstein, and Emir Abdullah, a Mother's Day card (?)
- Dialectica-International review of philosophy of knowledge, 1990 (Box 32)
  Vol. 44, memorial issue